[MUSIC]
[음악]
But a question is how are we gonna make these recommendations?
그렇다면 어떻게 추천을 할까요?
How are we gonna guess what rating a person would give to a movie that they've
누군가 아직 안 본 영화에 대해
never watched?
어떤 별점을 줄지 어떻게 추측할까요?
Well let's imagine for
잠시 각 영화와 사용자에 대한
a moment that we have some set of features about each movie and each user.
특징 세트가 있다고 상상해봅시다
So for example, we know that.
예를 들어
Movie v, which, in this case, is The Shawshank Redemption,
영화 v, 이 경우 쇼생크 탈출인데
Is about some set of different genres, like action, and romance, and drama.
액션, 로맨스, 드라마와 같은 여러 장르의 혼합이죠
And so we have this vector for each of these things,
이 벡터로 그걸 나타내는데
which says it's 0.3 about action It's 0.01, about romance.
0.3만큼 액션이고 0.01만큼 로맨스입니다
It's 1.5 about drama.
1.5만큼 드라마고요
And we have the set of things, so we know what the movie is about.
이걸 가지고 어떤 영화인지 알 수 있죠
And likewise, for every user, like this user you.
비슷한 방식으로 각 사용자에 대해
We know which of these different genres got user likes,
어떤 장르를 좋아하는지 알아냅니다
so for this user, we have a vector that says that for
이 사용자의 벡터에 따르면
action, this user really, really,
액션을 아주 아주 좋아하고
really likes action, really does not like romance.
로맨스는 그다지 좋아하지 않네요
Kind of likes drama and so on.
드라마는 그럭저럭 좋아합니다
And we're gonna call this first vector the movie vector, RV.
첫 번째 영화 벡터를 RV라 부를게요
We're gonna call this user specific vector, LU.
사용자별 벡터를 LU라 부릅니다
So let's say we know this, then what would you do to make a prediction of a rating?
이걸 안다면 별점 예측을 어떻게 할까요?
Well, one thing that might make sense is to take this movie vector and
영화 벡터와 사용자 벡터를 보고
this user vector and see how much they agree.
얼마나 일치하는지 보는 것도 방법이겠죠
If they agree a lot,
많이 일치한다면
then we'd guess that the person would rate that movie very highly.
영화를 높게 평가하리라 추측합니다
If they don't agree a lot then we're gonna say that it's probably very likely that
일치가 적다면 영화를 좋아하지 않아서
they will not like that movie and give it a low rating.
낮은 별점을 줄 확률이 높다고 예측합니다
So we're gonna estimate our rating.
별점을 추정해보죠
That's why we put this hat over it to denote that this is an estimate of how
여기 ^를 씌운 이유가 그것인데 사용자 u가
much the user, u, is going to like some movie v that they've never seen before.
아직 안 본 영화 v에 대한 선호도 추정입니다
And so the way we're gonna do this is just like when we're measuring similarity
방법은 두 문서 간 유사도 측정과 비슷한데
between two documents, we're gonna take the two vectors,
두 벡터에서
in that case that might have been a vector of different topics for the document,
그때는 문서의 여러 주제에 대한 벡터였는데
in this case we're talking about a vector of different topics about the movie.
지금은 영화의 여러 주제에 대한 벡터가 되죠
And so here we're gonna take these vectors,
이 벡터들을 보면
so 0.3, 0.01, 1.5, and so on.
0.3, 0.01, 1.5로 이어지는데
And we're gonna multiply it,
원소별로
element wise, by this vector.
이 벡터에 곱합니다
So this is our Rv.
이게 Rv입니다
This is our Lu.
이게 Lu고요
And what we're gonna get
이제 계산을
out is we're gonna get
해보면
out 0.3 x 2.5 + 0
0.3 x 2.5 + 0
+ 1.5 x 0.8 and so on.
+ 1.5 x 0.8로 이어지는데
And let's just say this ends up being some number like 7.2.
7.2가 결과값이 된다고 하죠
Just made that up.
그냥 만들어낸 숫자입니다
But if the user vector
사용자 벡터가 영화와 거의
really disagreed with what the movie was, so let's choose another color.
일치하지 않았다고 하죠 다른 색을 고르겠습니다
So this is some other user.
이건 다른 사용자입니다
Let's call this user Lu-prime.
Lu'라고 하죠
And let's say their vector said they really don't like action,
이 벡터는 액션을 전혀 안 좋아하고
they love romance.
로맨스를 사랑하며
They really hate drama.
드라마를 싫어한다고 하네요
And so on.
이렇습니다
Well here, the score is gonna be much lower, so
점수는 훨씬 낮아지겠죠
we're gonna get 0+3., sorry.
0+3 죄송합니다
Just for consistency +0.01 x 3.5
일관성을 위해 0.01 x 3.5
+ 1.5 x 0.01 + all these other numbers
+ 1.5 x 0.01 + 다른 숫자도
that really don't agree with one another,
그다지 일치하지 않는 걸 보니
and maybe this would come out to be
0.8과 같이
some small number like 0.8.
작은 숫자가 될 거 같네요
So the point here is that when the movie vector and
중요한 점은 영화 벡터와 사용자 벡터가
the user vector agree a lot, we'll get a much larger number than when they don't.
일치하면 안할 때보다 큰 수가 나오다는 것입니다
So we're gonna estimate a much larger rating
불일치할 때보다 훨씬 큰 별점일 거라
then in the case where they disagree.
추정할 수 있죠
And then when we think about making our recommendations, what are we gonna do?
추천은 어떻게 하죠?
Well, we'll just sort over all movies that we've predicted for that users.
사용자를 대상으로 예측한 모든 영화를 정렬해보죠
We'll sort by their predicted rating and
예측된 별점으로 정렬한 다음
then we'll recommend those with the largest ratings.
가장 별점이 높은 영화를 추천합니다
And I wanna highlight one thing here.
하나를 강조드리고 싶은데요
So if you remember the rating scale was between one and five or rather zero and
평가 등급이 1에서 5 또는 진짜
five we could provide no stars if you really hated a movie.
영화가 싫었다면 0에서 5라고 하죠
But the maximum score was a five, but
최고 점수는 5인데 우리가 예측한 값 중
note here that one of our predictions is 7.2 which is clearly greater than five.
하나는 7.2로 분명히 5보다 높습니다
So, with this type of model that we're talking about here We're not restricted.
이런 유형의 모델에서는 제한이 없습니다
There's nothing enforcing that we're gonna stay within a score of zero to five.
점수를 0에서 5 사이로 강제하는 게 없죠
But we can still use this to make recommendations because we just look at
이걸로도 추천은 할 수 있는데 점수가
the movies with the largest scores, even though those scores
꼭 별점을 정확히 표현한다고 볼 수 없기 때문에
aren't necessarily representative of exactly how many stars a movie would get.
점수가 가장 큰 영화를 추천하면 됩니다
[MUSIC]
[음악]